<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ lifted up, or, The heads of the chief controverted points, preached by Mr. Iohn Goodwin, pastor of Colman-street London, which hath bin the pretended grounds of the opposition that he hath had, by some other ministers, printed from a coppie written with his own hand, for the use of some who live under his owne charge. And now published by a friend of his, for the generall vievv of all men</title>
            <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41484</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213804</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826077</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30469</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41484)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30469)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1760:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ lifted up, or, The heads of the chief controverted points, preached by Mr. Iohn Goodwin, pastor of Colman-street London, which hath bin the pretended grounds of the opposition that he hath had, by some other ministers, printed from a coppie written with his own hand, for the use of some who live under his owne charge. And now published by a friend of his, for the generall vievv of all men</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, John, 1594?-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A (-A8, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30469:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30469:1"/>
            <p>CHRIST
lifted up,
OR,
The heads of the chief Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted
Points, Preached
By M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Goodwin,</hi> Paſtor of
<hi>Colman-ſtreet London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which hath bin the pretended grounds
of the oppoſition that he hath had, by
ſome other Miniſters,</p>
            <p>Printed from a Coppie written with his own
hand, for the uſe of ſome who live under
his owne Charge.</p>
            <p>And now Publiſhed by a Friend of his, for the
generall view of all men.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Cor. 4. 5.</bibl>
               <p>Iudge nothing before the time.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:30469:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30469:2"/>
            <head>THE
EPISTLE
TO
THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Thought it not amiſſe to give a
ſhort account, wherefore I preſent
to the world this extract. I have
met with two ſorts of men that have
bin contrary in opinions concerning
theſe points Controverted: yet in this
they both agree, to Calumniate the
Author: But they are upon tryall
continually found (as I conceive) ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:30469:3"/>
as in true accompt neither know him,
nor yet what hath bin affirmed or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed
in the points Controverted; the
one ſort of Men (and the moſt learned
of the two in ſome kind of learning)
peremptorily affirme, that in ſome (or
all) of theſe points there is at the leaſt
Errour; others ſay Hereſie: nay that
which is yet worſe, no leſſe then Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy:
but how they doe to make this
appear I will not determine, but leave
to thoſe that know how to judge. The
other ſort of men on the contrary, they
ſay and affirm with no leſſe confidence,
that in deed and in truth, there is no
ſuch difference between M<hi>
                  <hi rend="sup">r.</hi> Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi>
and other men in the points Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted,
but ſay, <hi>that he might have
delivered his mind in the language of
<pb facs="tcp:30469:3"/>
other Miniſters, and ſo have preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
all differences:</hi> They affirme that
he hath ſaid nothing but what hath
bin generally ſaid by all others before
him for ſubſtance, onely he hath taken
to himſelfe ſome new way of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
out of an affectation (as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive)
of ſingularity, or vaine glory.
Now that the firſt ſort of theſe may
appeare to have layd their foundation
no otherwhere but in the Sands; and
the latter to have no foundation at all;
I have preſented theſe heads to the
view of Conſidering men, which may
be as ſo many rules to try and prove
them by, or lights to judge and diſcerne
which is in the right, whether either
or neither, which is the thing I ayme
at: <hi>God</hi>-willing in time the world
<pb facs="tcp:30469:4"/>
may injoy the ſumme of the ſeverall
diſcourſes at large in their ſeverall
Tracts, and in the meane time by this
taſt I hope wiſe men will be ſo wiſe, as
not to be found Judges of the things
they know not: which is the deſire</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Of thy well-wiſhing Friend.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:30469:4"/>
            <head>CHRIST
lifted up.</head>
            <p>1. CHRIST rejecteth no man
that cometh unto him by
Faith, for want of prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
Legall Preparations, by way of
terrour or humiliation for ſin, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6. 37.
<hi>Revel.</hi> 22. 17, &amp;c. Neither is there any
abſolute neceſſity of ſuch preparation,
in reſpect of <hi>God,</hi> in that work of his
whereby he infuſeth Faith, or enableth
a man to come unto <hi>Chriſt:</hi> but he who
juſtifieth the ungodly, is able to come
upon a man in the middeſt of the greateſt
and deepeſt unpreparedneſſe, and to
bring him to <hi>Chriſt</hi> immediately. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:30469:5"/>
hath he any where in Scripture, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined
or limited the execution of this his
power, ſo as to engage or bind himſelfe,
never to make Beleevers, but of the lump
or maſſe prepared by the Law. Neither
hath he impoſed any Commandement
upon unbeleevers, to prepare, diſpoſe, or
qualifie themſelvs for the guift or receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by Faith, by procuring their
hearts to be ſmitten or wounded by the
Law. Neither doth any ſuch ſmiting or
wounding by the Law, give any man any
more right or title of beleeving in <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
then others have, who have not bin ſo
ſmitten. But the grace of the Goſpell is
every wayes abſolutely, and intirely free
and open, to whoſoever is willing to
receive it, <hi>Rev. 22. 17. Joh.</hi> 3. 16. yea and
every man is bound to beleeve, in what
eſtate or condition ſoever the Goſpell
finds him: and not to reject the Grace of
<hi>God</hi> therein, or put off the worke of <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving,</hi>
upon any pretence or conceit of
unworthineſſe, through want of Legall
<pb facs="tcp:30469:5"/>
               <hi>humiliation.</hi> Neither is there any <hi>humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation</hi>
for ſin, truly acceptable unto <hi>God,</hi>
or neceſſarily accompanied with <hi>ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
but that which is wrought in a man,
upon, or after his beleeving, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6.
<hi>Ioh.</hi> 15. 5. which is the fitteſt time for ſuch
<hi>humiliation, (Zach.</hi> 12. 10.) how ſoever the
Commandement of being humbled for
ſin, lyeth upon unregenerate men alſo at
all times, though not in relation to their
future beleeving.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt</hi> juſtifieth the Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
neither as it is an <hi>habit,</hi> neither as an
<hi>act,</hi> neither as it is the <hi>worke</hi> of Man, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
as it is the <hi>worke</hi> or <hi>guift</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> nor
in regard of any intrinſecall vertue, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
property, quality or dignity what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
whether abſolute or relative, but
by vertue of that <hi>will, good pleaſure, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
or <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>God</hi> with his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
whereby he hath ſetled this great
Prerogative upon <hi>Faith,</hi> rather then upon
any other Grace, or act whatſoever, <hi>Joh.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:30469:6"/>
6. 40. <hi>Joh. 1. 12. Joh. 3. 16. Eph.</hi> 2. 8, &amp;c. And
is truly ſaid to juſtifie inſtrumentally in
this ſence, as it is means choſen and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified
by <hi>God,</hi> to bring men into commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
part and fellowſhip of that Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
and Redemption, which <hi>Chriſt</hi>
hath purchaſed: But to ſay, that Faith
juſtifieth, in relation to its object <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
or (which is the ſame) becauſe it layeth
hold on <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is to aſcribe a meritorious
efficiency to it in the work of <hi>juſtification,</hi>
and to ſeat the juſtifying nature or pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of it, in a property which is moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
intrinſecall, and eſſentiall to it: yea
and beſides, makes the love of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and
every other Grace that hath relation to
<hi>Chriſt</hi> as its object, to be juſtifying as well
as it.</p>
            <p>3. There is no Morall, Legall, or poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> conſiſting either in
<hi>habits,</hi> or <hi>acts,</hi> (or both) conformable to
the Morall Law, that is formally imputed
from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or derived upon a Beleever,
<pb facs="tcp:30469:6"/>
in his <hi>juſtification.</hi> But that <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi>
or <hi>juſtification,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
by his <hi>active</hi> and <hi>paſſive obedience</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
for thoſe that <hi>beleeve</hi> in him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts
wholly in <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, Rom.</hi> 4.
v. 5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 38, 39, &amp;c. which is
therfore called an <hi>imputed righteouſneſſe,</hi>
or a <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> without <hi>works, Rom.</hi> 4.
6, &amp;c. becauſe it is freely given, conferr'd,
or caſt upon a beleever, by <hi>God.</hi> And
becauſe <hi>Faith</hi> is anoynted or ſet apart by
<hi>God</hi> to this office or ſervice of bringing
in the Beleever into communion and
fellowſhip of this <hi>imputed righteouſneſſe</hi>
or <hi>juſtification</hi> purchaſed by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is
therfore it ſelfe ſaid to be imputed for,
or unto <hi>righteouſneſſe, Gen. 15. 6. Rom.</hi> 4.
5, &amp;c. that is, to be all that <hi>God</hi> now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth
of any man, for, or towards his
<hi>juſtification,</hi> or the <hi>forgiveneſſe</hi> of his <hi>ſins.</hi>
Neither is the obſervation of the Morall
Law, either by a mans ſelfe, or by ſurety,
any part of any mans <hi>juſtification:</hi> which
is compleat and intire, in the nature and
<pb facs="tcp:30469:7"/>
ſubſtance of it, without <hi>works, i. e.</hi> the
merit of <hi>works, Rom.</hi> 4. 6. though the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe
and procurement of it, on <hi>Chriſts</hi>
part, was by merit of <hi>works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>4. That <hi>Faith</hi> which preciſely juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
a ſinner in the ſight of <hi>God,</hi> is not the
beleeving any thing more, or any thing
beſides, what <hi>God</hi> himſelfe hath plainly
revealed in his Goſpell. Therfore truly
and ſoundly to beleeve the Goſpell, as it
cometh from <hi>God,</hi> or as it is delivered by
the Holy Ghoſt in the Scripture, is that
<hi>Faith</hi> which <hi>juſtifieth.</hi> The ſumme or
ſubſtance whereof, is uſually compriz'd
in theſe or the like Propoſitions, <hi>That
Jeſus Chriſt is that Son of God, that whoſoever
beleeves on him, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> &amp;c. Which
Euangelicall Oracles, whoſoever rightly
underſtandeth, and in a cordiall, firme,
and ſincere manner, and with his whole
heart beleeveth, is juſtified before <hi>God,
Joh. 20. 31. Act. 8 37. 1 Joh. 5. 1. 5, &amp;c.</hi> and
hath undoubted grounds to beleeve his
<pb facs="tcp:30469:7"/>
particular or perſonall <hi>ſalvation,</hi> in as full
and ſatisfying a manner, as he beleeves
the Goſpell it ſelfe. Neither is it poſſible
that any man, who thus beleeves the
Goſpell, and withall knows and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
what he beleeveth therein, but that
he ſhould make particular application
of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to himſelfe, and beleeve his own
<hi>ſalvation,</hi> becauſe all feares, doubts, and
queſtions whatſoever may be conceiv'd
or mov'd in the ſoule, touching his <hi>ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi>
are fully anſwered and taken
away by ſuch a Faith; As he that knows
and conſiders what a Rock is, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the ſtrength, firmneſſe, and ſtability
of it, unpoſſible it is, that he ſhould refuſe
to ſtand upon it for feare of ſinking,
becauſe all grounds and reaſons of this
feare, are fully taken away by ſuch a
knowledge and conſideration.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
